Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching the plane bagel. As you're
probably very much aware of at this
point, last Saturday we had a meaningful
escalation in the Venezuela US situation
as in the middle of the night we saw a
US Delta Force team invade the country
and capture Venezuela's president
Nicolas Maduro, extracting him to New
York to face a number of US federal
charges. A shocking update that followed
months of US military activity in the
region and something that's been met
with conflicted feelings, controversy,
and heated debate online. While Maduro
was largely viewed internationally as an
illegitimate ruler whose country has
suffered severely under his reign, the
US invading a country, plucking out its
leader and then bringing them to the US
to charge with crimes domestically
naturally sets a pretty wild precedent
and has led to some condemnation.
Especially because not long after this
event, Trump began making moves to
seemingly take advantage of the
country's oil output. You see, oil is
one of Venezuela's main industries,
making up about 80% of the country's
exports. And in fact, the country sits
on the largest oil reserve in the world
with a country hosting a fifth of the
world's total proven oil reserves. So,
while Donald Trump has attributed his
actions to a crackdown on Venezuela's
role in the fentanyl crisis, many
believe that the real motive behind all
this is really the oil, especially given
Venezuela's relatively minor role in
America's drug problem. And Trump hasn't
done a whole lot to beat those
allegations. The president has
previously demanded that the country
return supposedly stolen US oil assets.
And not long after the raid, the
president announced that the US would be
sending large oil companies to develop
and rebuild Venezuela's long neglected
oil infrastructure. With this also being
followed by news that the US would be
taking and selling 30 to 50 million
barrels of oil from the country to quote
benefit the people of Venezuela and the
United States and announcing plans to
control the country's sales
indefinitely. Now, looking past the
moral implications of invading a country
and exploiting its natural resources,
which yes, is a big one, but but looking
past that for a second, some people have
really run with this idea that the US
could convert Venezuela into an energy
powerhouse, whether for Venezuela's
benefit or their own. uh with some going
so far as to argue that the US economy
is about to boom from all the supposedly
free oil it's about to receive and some
even warning of the meaningful risk this
all poses to Canada given that the
country sends about 97% of its oil
exports to the US and could potentially
see this substituted with imports from
Venezuela. But is this a realistic risk?
Can America really just go in, capture
all of Venezuela's oil output and then
replace its reliance on Canada here? Or
is it all just wishful thinking? Well,
that's what I wanted to cover in today's
video. And naturally, the controversial
and exploitive nature of all this makes
it a really ugly topic to discuss. And
of course, the future of the oil markets
is far from the most important aspect to
this update, right? Millions of
Venezuelans now face severe uncertainty
regarding the future of their country
and economy. It's unclear how beneficial
America's involvement will be, whether
they truly help rebuild the country and
benefit its economy, as Trump has
suggested, or simply exploit a
vulnerable nation for its natural
resources. But today I want to narrow
the scope to that discussion of oil and
whether the US could feasibly meet its
oil needs with Venezuelan exports
because we have seen markets react to
this. Canadian oil companies fell in
price on Monday while US companies
actually jumped in value. But also I'm
not a geopolitical expert so I can't
really speak to some of the greater
unknowns uh with this situation. What I
can do is try to clear up some of the
misinformation specifically around oil
and gas, which as a Canadian investment
analyst, I've researched quite a bit to
give more context that's seemingly
missing from a lot of this online
discussion about oil from Venezuela. And
extend the conversation to its impact on
the Canadian market. And this not to
label any of this as good or bad.
Frankly, it's just not that simple. It
would be great if Venezuela were able to
rebuild and uh prosper from its oil
industry. We're just going to focus on
feasibility here and the risk this poses
to Canada's own oil industry. But let's
start with a bit of background on
Venezuela.
How did we get here? Well, as you may
know, Venezuela is a country who in the
past was a very prosperous nation in
South America thanks to its oil wealth.
The country nationalized its oil
industry in 1976, creating the state-run
PDVSA oil company and further
expropriating assets in the 2000s from
several foreign oil companies. with a
country generally able to grow its
economy amid years of high oil prices.
However, over the past few decades,
Venezuela's economy has deteriorated
meaningfully due to its dependence on
oil, mismanagement of its economy,
sanctions from other countries, and
corruption within the government with a
good chunk of this happening under
Maduro's leadership. You see, Maduro was
elected in 2013 following the previous
leader's death and continued a trend
from Chavez of eroding democratic
institutions, consolidating power at the
executive branch, and targeting civil
liberties with Maduro accused of rigging
elections to hold on to power in
violently cracking down on disscent.
Something that led the US and a number
of other nations to announce sanctions
against the country and specific members
of Maduro's regime. In particular, in
2019, the US imposed a complete embargo
on transactions with PDVSA, effectively
cutting off exports to key markets like
India and the European Union. And as a
result of these factors and an oil glut
in the mid2010s, Venezuela saw its
economy decimated. DDP contracted to
less than a third of its size from 2012
to 2025. The country experienced a bout
of hyperinflation that saw prices rising
by hundreds of thousands of percentage
points. And oil production, which peaked
for the country at around 3.5 million
barrels per day, fell by over 2/3 to
today just around 1 million barrels per
day. In fact, despite the country
sitting on a fifth of the total proven
oil reserves globally, production today
sits at around just 1% of the world's
total output. Now, the US has long been
putting pressure on the Maduro regime.
But things really escalated last year
when the US began bombing civilian boats
accused of fing drugs and imposing a
complete naval blockade against
sanctioned oil tankers in December with
Trump accusing the country of
contributing to America's fentanyl
crisis and even stealing US assets.
Something likely related to the
expropriation of assets in 2007 when
companies like Exxon Mobile and Kico
Phillips were bought out of their
Venezuelan operations for a fraction of
their worth. In fact, Chevron today is
the only US company that's been able to
maintain operations in Venezuela through
joint ventures through all these years.
But this past weekend, things took a
very unexpected turn when over the span
of just 2 hours and 20 minutes, the US
attacked Venezuela, captured Maduro, and
extracted him from the country with the
dictator and his wife being brought to
New York where he's pleaded not guilty
to charges of narotism conspiracy,
cocaine importation conspiracy, and
possession of machine guns and
destructive devices. Now, since this
update, the US has maintained its
blockade on Venezuelan oil, even
intercepting a Russian oil tanker
accused of transporting oil from the
country. And Trump has suggested that
the US would run the country in the
interim. But Trump has quickly shifted
the focus of all this from drugs to oil,
uh, presenting this as a development
opportunity for the country's oil
industry. And it's that aspect of the
story that has raised questions over how
this all might impact Canada's trade
with the US when it comes to crude oil.
You see, Canada and Venezuela actually
both predominantly produce the same type
of heavy sour crude oil, which is a type
of thick, hard to extract oil with a
high sulfur content that's generally
harder to process than sweet light oil
and also generally produces lower value
end products. Uh, with it commonly being
used for ashvalt and industrial fuels.
However, the US has long built a lot of
its oil infrastructure to specifically
handle and refine this type of heavy
oil. In fact, back in the early 2000s,
the US used to import about half of
Venezuela's 3.5 million barrels a day.
And even as recent as 2023 was still
importing about 23% of the country's
total exports, with the US having a good
chunk of its refining capacity right on
the Gulf Coast, where it's able to
receive oil from Venezuela via tanker.
Now today, with Venezuela producing
around 1 million barrels per day, even
if the US were to absorb 100% of this
export, it would still represent only
about 17% of America's total crude oil
imports, compared to Canada, which
currently supplies around 65% of
America's crude oil imports. But with
the sheer size of Venezuela's oil
reserves, there's the concern that if
the US builds out this infrastructure
and takes all of this output, either by
commerce or exploitation, that they
could completely replace the imports
coming from Canada, which is meaningful
for the country given that Canada's oil
is effectively landlocked. Oil
production occurs predominantly in the
middle of Canada and Alberta. And while
there is infrastructure reaching to the
country's west coast, most pipelines are
directed towards the US where the
country sends 80% of its produced oil.
with attempts by Alberta to expand
pipeline capacity out west long being
held up federally and by British
Columbia and amid heightened tensions
between Canada and the US during the
trade war and the comments around
turning the country into the 51st state
via economic pressure. This has
naturally increased a lot of anxieties
in the country. But how likely is it for
Canada to be replaced here? Well, it's
incredibly early in the whole Venezuela
situation, but there are some pretty big
holes in this idea of completely
substituting Canadian oil. Firstly,
there's the matter of regional
infrastructure in the United States.
Yes, it is true that Canadian and
Venezuelan oil is similar and could
theoretically be substituted for one
another at America's heavy oil refining
facilities, a good chunk of which are
located on that Gulf of Mexico. But even
still, the US doesn't actually have the
infrastructure to immediately substitute
its Canadian oil imports. As a bit of
background, the US is divided into five
petroleum administration for defense
districts or pads for short. The Gulf
Coast refineries in pad 3 have a
cumulative capacity of 9.8 million
barrels per day and is only at a 90%
utilization. So, while these facilities
could technically absorb all of
Venezuela's output without impacting its
imports from other countries to these
facilities, this is most likely where we
could see Canadian oil substituted for
Venezuelan oil. But the thing is, PAD 3
isn't where Canadian oil is
predominantly processed. Today, only
about 424,000 barrels per day are sent
to that district by Canada. Instead,
about 78% of Canada's crude oil exports
are processed in pad 2 and four inland
districts where 100% of the oil imported
by refineries comes from Canada and
where it's not really feasible to send
Venezuelan oil given that pipeline
infrastructure for crude oil tends to be
southbound and transporting via freight
is far less economic. Now, yes, there
could be substitution at the other pads
to offset lower processing of Canadian
oil at pad 2 and four, but given the
pipeline infrastructure that's been long
built out between Canada and the US,
it's unlikely that would be more
economic when you also factor in the
transportation needed to then get that
oil to its domestic and markets. And
building out the infrastructure to send
Venezuelan oil north within the United
States would take billions of dollars of
investment, state approvals, and years
of planning and construction. So right
away about 80% of Canada's oil doesn't
face immediate substitution risk from
Venezuelan oil given how America's
infrastructure is set up. Yes, the 50
million barrels could disrupt Canadian
imports temporarily, but the represents
less than 10 days of America's crude oil
import demand. Secondly, when we talk
about infrastructure on the Venezuelan
side, it's questionable whether there's
going to be much appetite from US firms
to repair the long neglected facilities
and pipelines. According to Francisco
Manaldi, director of the Latin America
Energy Program at the Center for Energy
Studies, Venezuela would need
investments in excess of $100 billion to
bring production above its peak to 4
million barrels per day in a decade,
which would be about the same as what
Canada is currently supplying to the US.
But because the National Oil Company is
bankrupt and the country itself is in
debt, there's not really any money
internally to make that investment. So,
they would have to rely on foreign
investment to develop its industry. Yet
political instability and corruption are
some of the biggest deterrence and risks
to foreign direct investment. Yes, one
would hope that with Maduro being ousted
that the country could begin its path
towards stabilization. Uh but these
things don't exactly resolve themselves
overnight. And so far anyway, it's not
looking promising that we've had
meaningful change in the country. The
country is currently being run by
Maduro's vice president, Deli Rodriguez,
while Maduro's cabinet members remain in
place. And since Maduro's capture, the
government has declared a 90-day state
of emergency with pro Maduro armed
militias now searching phones in the
capital of Caracus and arresting
journalists and citizens who spoke in
support of Maduro's capture. So despite
how it's been framed by some, the
country hasn't exactly been liberated.
There's also the belief that the
toppling of Maduro leaves the country
open to a violent power struggle between
armed groups, especially given that the
US hasn't maintained any sort of
presence in the country to help address
any sort of a power vacuum. So you can
imagine the challenges US companies
would face trying to develop oil
infrastructure in a country where armed
groups are actively hostile against US
involvement. Now Trump has suggested
that Rodriguez is fully cooperating with
the US and publicly the interim
president has stated that she is open to
energy relations where all parties
benefit. But a common view between
Maduro's regime and the opposition party
is that Venezuelans should be the main
beneficiary of the country's oil
production, not the US. which might make
the headline about handing over $3
billion worth of oil a bit bizarre, but
that oil is largely stranded due to the
US embargo. So, it really just presents
a way for the country to try and
recuperate losses on oil that's likely
actively costing it money to store. It
doesn't necessarily represent a
willingness to work with the US longer
term. Not to mention that a good chunk
of Venezuela's skilled labor in the oil
industry has actually long fled the
nation for countries like Canada because
of the country's political instability.
So, with all that's in the air regarding
Venezuela's government, it's
questionable whether the region will be
able to attract this talent back to
Venezuela. And beyond all of this, it
just might not make economic sense. The
global oil market is currently overs
supplied. The International Energy
Agency projects a surplus of 3.8 million
barrels per day in global oil markets
this year, something that's been
dragging down benchmark prices for oil.
Not to mention that heavy oil like what
Venezuela produces actually sells at a
discount to the widely cited West Texas
Intermediate which is for sweet light
oil. Western Canadian Select for example
which is Canada's heavy oil price
benchmark currently sits at $45 a barrel
compared to WTI around $60. Clauddio
Galenberti the chief economist and
global director of market analysis at
Rystat Energy estimates that the break
even price for oil development in
Venezuela is around $80 a barrel. So
beyond the operating net back, the
profitability you would see with
existing infrastructure likely being
negative, it doesn't make a whole lot of
economic sense to go to a country with
armed regimes hostile to you, spend
billions of dollars on developing
infrastructure, waiting through years of
planning, development, and construction
only to produce more unprofitable oil,
all while the market is currently in
over supply. In fact, another estimate
by Rice Energy even suggests that the
country needs $53 billion over the next
15 years just to keep Venezuela's crude
oil production flat with there only
being an estimated 300,000 barrels per
day of additional supply that could be
brought online with limited incremental
spending. So, yes, in the short term, we
could see the US begin substituting a
portion of its Canadian imports with oil
from Venezuela. Uh, but the amount of
infrastructure investment needed to
expand Venezuelan oil production and
refining in the US just doesn't make a
lot of economic sense in the current
environment. That could change in the
future. Prices could fluctuate higher.
Trump has suggested he could subsidize
companies who go and help develop
Venezuela's infrastructure and
technology could improve the net back of
production in Venezuela. Canada's own
heavy oil production has itself managed
to achieve low-cost production despite
the complex nature of its operations.
But in a recent meeting with oil
executives where Trump pushed to achieve
a $100 billion investment commitment,
Exxon CEO Darren Woods went so far as to
describe Venezuela as uninvestable. And
while Chevron, who currently accounts
for about a fifth of the country's
production, is expected to bolster
output, some experts only anticipate
investments in the $50 million range,
far from what would be needed to
revolutionize the industry. And that's
all without considering the other
players in all this. There are of course
other world powers like China and Russia
who Venezuela is actually in debt to who
likely won't be too keen about the US
taking its tankers and cutting off its
key oil supplier with China previously
estimated to be buying up to 3/4 of
Venezuela's embargoed oil. Other Latin
American leaders and even American
allies will likely push back against any
attempt at adventurism in Venezuela. And
even within the US, it's very likely we
see political push back to American
involvement in a foreign country. Now,
for Canada's part, it also will take
many years to build out the
infrastructure needed to sell oil to
other markets. But the country has been
making some progress in diversifying its
reliance on the US here. In May 2024,
the country completed its Trans Mountain
pipeline expansion, which tripled
pipeline capacity to its West Coast to
nearly 900,000 barrels per day. And the
federal government recently signed an
agreement with Alberta to kickstart the
construction of another pipeline to its
coast. Now, none of this is to say that
Canadian oil companies don't face any
risk with this update. Uh the truth is
that any added supply to the market is
going to hurt the price that oil
producers are able to sell for. And with
enough investment, really anything is
possible here. The US could even develop
its infrastructure and shut out all
crude oil imports by relying completely
on domestically produced oil if it chose
to do so. But hopefully this video
helped to explain the nuance of the
situation and why toppling Maduro is
hardly enough to bring stability back to
the region as we've seen with the
toppling of dictators in other
countries, let alone enough to enable
the US to begin a US enterprise in
Venezuela. It would be great if this was
the first step towards stability in the
region and if Venezuelan people are able
to benefit and prosper from the
development of their oil industry and
other important sectors. But the truth
is today we're just far from that
reality. Anyway, that's the video. I
hope you found it helpful. If you did,
please do make sure to like, subscribe,
all that good stuff. It does help the
channel tremendously. And let me know
your thoughts on the updates we've seen
in Venezuela. Uh, thanks again for
joining me. And as always, be safe out